Packet River 101

A Hands-On Training Syllabus for the Packet River Cyber Range

By Britley Hoff

2026 Edition

The attacks that are actually taking down infrastructure are boring. Not a zero-day, not a nation-state exploit chain. A home router still on admin / admin. A login sent in the clear. A password reused somewhere it should not have been. A message bus that will take an instruction from anyone. String three of those together and you are standing in front of a rail switch.

Packet River is a small town you break into for a high score, and it is built entirely out of those boring attacks. One live map shows the whole place running: traffic cycling through four crossroads, a train on its loop, water and power flowing to the houses, a clean river with people swimming in it. Every building on that map is also a real, deliberately vulnerable service. You scan it and attack it with the same open-source tools you would use on a real engagement, pull the flag hidden inside the exploit, submit it, and watch the town break on screen. Then you hit reset and try again, faster, or quieter.

It is the third in a family with Widgetorium, a vulnerable web-application lab, and Cross Creek, an ICS/OT range. Same idea, learn by doing, except this one keeps score.

How this book is different from the range's own docs

Packet River deliberately does not ship a copy-paste path to owning the town in thirty minutes. This syllabus is the same. Every session below gives you the class of bug, the tool family, the surface to look at, what you will see when it works, and the fix, with its real-world parallel and its MITRE ATT&CK mapping. It does not hand you the exact request, the credential, the parameter, or the flag's hiding place. That tier, the sharp step-by-step, lives in instructor/answer-key.md in the repo, for people running a class. The range also has an opt-in hint that costs points, and hidden notes scattered around the town that cost only the looking.

Standing up the range

Packet River is one docker-compose stack. Every published port binds to 127.0.0.1; start.sh refuses to launch if any port would bind past loopback, and the attacker box has no route off the lab.

cd packetriver
./setup.sh              # preflight, build the images
./start.sh             # bring the town up with the deliberate weaknesses on
./status.sh            # health, the loopback bind audit, the containment probe
./start.sh --segmented # the defended town, for Session 6
./reset.sh             # restore the golden state between cohorts

Then open http://127.0.0.1:8080/, sign up, and start a run. The attacker workstation is a container:

docker compose exec player sh
ls /opt/pktr/scripts

Toggle | Default | What it does
PKT_EVENTS | calm | timed events: a news crew, a state inspector, a Founder's Day parade (Session 1)
PKT_EGGS | off | subtle or obvious scatters in-world hint fragments
PKT_LIGHT | unset | skips the bundled attacker box; bring your own shell

What it is built from

Polyglot on purpose, so recon and fingerprinting are realistic: PHP/Apache for Main Street, Node/Express for the bank, Python/Flask for the payment gateway and the soft-PLCs, a real CoreDNS server, a real net-snmp agent, real Modbus/TCP, real MQTT, web3270's own TN5250 and TN3270 mocks for the green screens. The game's own pieces, the map server and the scoreboard, stay single-language. The attacker box carries nmap, sqlmap, ffuf, curl, dig, mosquitto-clients, pymodbus, the net-snmp clients, tcpdump, dsniff, and a set of thin Python wrappers under /opt/pktr/scripts.

Authorised use

Use Packet River only: on your own machine; in a lab you control; in a classroom or range where you have permission; under written rules of engagement for authorised training or assessment. Never point a Packet River command, script, payload, scan, or credential at a real system you do not own. Some of these attacks have physical consequences in the real world. This range exists so you never have to learn that on a live one.

Session 1: The Town, the Score, and the Noise You Make

Goal for this session: understand what you are looking at, how the score works, and why being loud costs you. No exploits yet. By the end you should be able to start a run, open a target, read the Alert meter, and reset the town.

1.1 The map is the truth

The map is a pixel-art isometric drawing of Packet River, population 646, with a transparent live overlay on top. Everything that lights up, floods, or goes dark is driven off a state snapshot the map server broadcasts once a second. Traffic cycles green and red. A train runs the top track and loops off screen. Water and power flow to thirty-odd house markers. The river runs clean with swimmers in it.

Click any building and its real service opens in a side panel, starting with a login portal, the same convention as the Cross Creek HMIs and the Widgetorium login. When you land an exploit and submit its flag, the map degrades: a shop goes defaced or db_dumped or carded, a feeder trips and a zone goes dark, the sewage plant's outfall runs raw and a brown mosaic spreads from the swimming beach, the rail switch throws and the train runs the spur into the widget factory and it catches fire.

1.2 Flags are the only currency

There is no "award points" endpoint. The scoreboard mints a random PKTR{...} flag per technique at boot and drops each one into the single service that owns it, inside the vulnerable resource, in a spot that requires the actual exploit to reach. The only write path is POST /api/score/submit {flag}. Points are a pure server-side function of a valid random flag plus server-held timing and Alert state. No client-supplied score, multiplier, or "technique complete" field is trusted.

The formula rewards three things: speed (a decaying multiplier from arm to submit), stealth (a bonus if the Alert Level did not rise while you worked the technique), and chaining (a stacking bonus for distinct techniques solved on the same subsystem in one run). Call arm when you start recon on a technique so the clock and the stealth baseline start then.

1.3 The Alert Level, and the blue team

A leaky-bucket "heat" accumulator with a roughly two-minute half-life drives an Alert Level from 0 (calm) to 5 (lockdown). Heat comes from the inherent loudness of what you did (a payroll drain is loud however quietly you got admin), from wrong flag submissions, and from a tailer reading the gateway's access log for scan bursts and tool user-agents. Thresholds have downward hysteresis so the meter does not flap.

Each level the meter crosses, a blue team responds, and a couple of the responses actually bite:

Level | Response
1 | SOC investigating (banner)
2 | credentials rotated on the field controllers and the HMIs: an in-progress attacker's next canned command fails
3 | rate limiting (banner; the segmented build wires it for real)
4 | OT segmentation (banner; the segmented build drops the routes)
5 | automatic golden-restore of the worst-hit subsystem

Already-solved techniques stay solved. But if you are mid-chain when Level 2 fires and you were relying on a default credential, you just lost it.

1.4 Timed events: the town has a clock

With PKT_EVENTS at calm or lively, three things happen on a schedule and change the stakes:

News crew. A TV crew parks at whatever is most broken. While they film, any Alert heat from an incident on that subsystem is multiplied. Getting caught loud on camera is worse than getting caught loud.
State inspector. An inspector visits for a fixed window. An incident that is still active when they leave costs a large heat spike and a citation, if the town was clean when they arrived. It rewards cleaning up your mess, or never being seen.
Founder's Day parade. Parade crowds fill the crossroads. A signal hijacked to all-green during the parade racks up crashes several times faster. Same exploit, far bigger consequence, if you time it.

1.5 Reset

The in-game reset panel restores one subsystem, or the whole town, to golden state over the bus without a container bounce, and re-arms a fresh flag for that scope. ./reset.sh -y from the shell is the harder hammer, and also clears the scoreboard run state. Reset between cohorts, and any time the town gets into a state you did not intend.

1.6 What you should notice

Nothing here required a memory-corruption bug or a piece of malware. The whole range is misconfiguration, missing authentication, cleartext, and reused credentials. That is the point, and it is what the rest of this book is about.

Session 2: Main Street

Goal for this session: work eight storefronts, one bug class each, so no two teach the same thing. They are all vhosts on one shared PHP/Apache container, published on 127.0.0.1:8090 and reachable by name through the gateway (generalstore.packetriver.range and so on), each behind a login portal. The tool is whatever fits the bug. The map effect is always the storefront changing status.

2.1 The eight

Shop | Bug class | Tool family | What you will see
General Store | error-based SQL injection in the product search, verbose DB errors on | sqlmap, or a hand-built UNION | the database walks you through its own schema; shop reads db_dumped
Hardware & Supply | IDOR on an order lookup, the record id trusted, never checked against your session | curl / ffuf walking the id | other people's orders; shop reads db_dumped
Pharmacy | authentication bypass in the portal login, the query string-built | a crafted username; sqlmap also finds it | a session with no valid password; records leaked
Diner | a database backup left under the web root | content discovery (ffuf), or read what the pages give away | the dump downloads; shop reads db_dumped
Barbershop | stored XSS in the booking form, picked up by an automated "manager" review that is a regex, never a real browser | a script payload in a booking note | the review fires in the manager's context; shop reads defaced
Tavern | default credentials on the POS/jukebox admin, weak session token | the vendor default, or hydra a short list | an admin session; shop reads carded
Dry Cleaners | an exposed .git directory with a secret in deleted history | git-dumper, then read the log | the repo reconstructs; a key in an old commit; shop reads db_dumped
Bait & Tackle | SSRF in a "fetch product image by URL" feature | curl pointing the fetch at something only the server can reach | an internal response comes back in the page; shop reads db_dumped

2.2 Real-world parallels

None of these are exotic. The LIKE-clause concatenation is the shape behind countless breaches (CWE-89). Broken object-level authorization is OWASP API Security number one; the Panera Bread and USPS "Informed Visibility" leaks were mass IDOR. Exposed .git is a standing bug-bounty find (CWE-527). SSRF to something only the server can reach is Capital One, 2019 (CWE-918). Default credentials on a point-of-sale admin is Mirai's entire business model (CWE-1392).

2.3 MITRE ATT&CK

Almost everything here is T1190 (exploit public-facing application) into T1213 (data from information repositories). The barber's stored XSS is T1059.007. The default-cred tavern is T1078.001. The Bait & Tackle SSRF opens the door to T1046 (network service discovery) against the internal side.

2.4 The fixes

Shop | Fix
General Store | parameterised queries; verbose errors off in production
Hardware | enforce ownership on every record read
Pharmacy | prepared statements and a real credential check
Diner | keep backups out of the docroot; block archive extensions at the server
Barbershop | output-encode on render; add a CSP; treat back-office views as untrusted-input surfaces
Tavern | force a credential change on first use; issue real session tokens
Dry Cleaners | do not deploy the repo; block dotfiles at the server; rotate anything that was ever committed
Bait & Tackle | allowlist egress, block loopback and link-local and internal ranges, do not return the raw fetch body

2.5 The recon layer

The shops share one container, but the gateway hands each vhost a distinct Server and X-Powered-By header, so app-layer fingerprinting still tells them apart. That is deliberate. Real shared hosting looks exactly like this, and a good recon pass notices the difference between "Apache/2.4.58 (Ubuntu) with PHP/7.4.33" and "LiteSpeed, no PHP header" even when both answer on the same IP.

Session 3: City Hall, the Money, and the Green Screens

Goal for this session: drain the town's money three different ways, and see why a modern web front door and a fifty-year-old terminal host end up at the same place. This is the civic tier, the payment gateway, First Packet Bank & Trust, and the two mainframes behind them.

3.1 City Hall, Police, Fire

Target | Bug class | Map effect
Town Hall announcements | weak clerk login, then a notice stored raw and rendered raw on the public board (stored XSS / defacement) | the announcement board on the map shows your text; Town Hall defaced
Town Hall payslip viewer | path traversal in a document parameter, reached after a weak payroll login | payroll balance to zero, admin_pwned
Police blotter | the dispatch team's config file is world-readable under the web root | Police defaced
Fire station alarm panel | a shared default credential | Fire defaced
Payment gateway | IDOR on GET /receipt/<txn>: no auth, sequential ids, and one seeded receipt's memo carries the flag | fraud spreads: every healthy shop flips to carded

The card data in the gateway is vendor test PANs only, non-functional, and the header of paygw/cards.py says so. LFI is CWE-22 / OWASP A01; secrets in a web-served config file is CWE-538 / OWASP A05; the receipt IDOR is OWASP API1:2023 and a PCI-DSS 7 failure.

3.2 The bank

First Packet Bank & Trust is a Node/Express app on 127.0.0.1:8100: a login portal, a customer dashboard, a JSON accounts API, and a staff-only transfer form. Two ways in:

The token check honours alg:none. Re-issue your own customer token with an elevated role and no signature, and the staff dashboard opens and prints the Fed wire settlement token in the clear. This is CVE-2015-9235 and a decade of copies since; MITRE T1550.001. Fix: pin the algorithm, reject none, verify the signature, and do not render a settlement token into HTML.
The accounts API has no ownership check. Walk the account ids and one memo carries a municipal reconciliation token. OWASP API1:2023 again. Fix: enforce ownership on every account read; keep secrets out of free-text fields.

Draining the bank fires bank_drain: carded, balance zero, ATM drained, and the alarm panel, which is wired to the industrial power feeder, drops on the map.

3.3 The AS/400 behind City Hall

A real TN5250 host on 127.0.0.1:8992: a SIGNON panel, a menu tree, and Interactive SQL. Three stacked IBM i misconfigurations, all real: a blank password is accepted for any profile, the way unhardened low-QSECURITY boxes behaved; a powerful profile still has its shipped default password; and the payroll library is left readable to the public, so any signed-on profile can read it from STRSQL. Drive it with the bundled as400_5250.py, or hand-drive from the browser terminal. Submitting fires the same cityhall_payroll effect as the web LFI path: the money is gone whichever way you got in.

Fix: set QSECURITY to 40 or above, require passwords, rotate the shipped defaults, restrict powerful profiles' device access, and pull *PUBLIC on the payroll library down to *EXCLUDE with an authorization list. Default and blank IBM i credentials are a standing finding in every AS/400 security review, and *PUBLIC *ALL on application libraries is the single most common IBM i exposure.

3.4 The IBM z16 behind the bank

Core banking on a z/OS LPAR: a real TN3270E host with a RACF logon panel, TSO READY, and a RACF command family (LISTUSER, RLIST, SETROPTS LIST). Two paths:

z16_racf. A default admin was never revoked; it still holds SPECIAL and OPERATIONS and still logs on with its shipped password. A banking transfer-approval profile is world-readable and in WARNING mode, so a failed access check is logged but allowed, the control is fail-open, and someone parked a reconciliation key in that profile's readable metadata. A never-revoked default admin is a standing pen-test finding on z/OS; WARNING mode left in place for years is a classic audit hit.
z16_apf. LISTAPF flags a library that is APF-authorised and also world-writable. An APF library you can write to is an APF library you can subvert: link a routine in, CALL it, and you are running in supervisor state, key 0, with total control of the LPAR. "World-writable APF library" is one of the highest-severity findings a z/OS review can produce, and it is not rare. It is a straight line from UPDATE on a dataset to key 0.

Both fire bank_drain. Fix for the RACF path: revoke the default admin or strip its authority and rotate it, take the profile out of WARNING, set UACC(NONE) with an access list, SETROPTS PROTECTALL(FAILURES), and never put secrets in profile metadata. Fix for the APF path: no writable APF libraries, tight authority on the volumes that hold them, program control on APF modules, and audit every APF-list change.

3.5 What you should notice

Five different technologies, one outcome. The web app trusts a token's own claim about how it was signed. The API trusts a number in the URL. The AS/400 trusts a blank password. The z16 trusts a default admin nobody removed, and a dataset permission nobody checked. The money does not care which door you came through.

Session 4: The Utilities

Goal for this session: make the physical town misbehave. Water, power, the widget-factory line, and sewage are real Modbus/TCP soft-PLCs. Traffic is commanded over an open MQTT bus. Rail is a raw-TCP console. There are no memory-corruption exploits in this session, because none of these protocols require one.

4.1 Modbus has no opinion about who you are

Modbus/TCP is from 1979. Request-response over port 502, reading and writing coils (single bits: pump run commands, keyswitches) and registers (16-bit words: setpoints, sensor values). No authentication, no session, no signing. If you can open the port, you are the HMI as far as the PLC is concerned. FrostyGoop, the malware that took the heat out of 600 buildings in Lviv in January 2024, used function code 6, write single register, the same call the HMI makes every second.

PLC | Port | What a write does
water | 127.0.0.1:5502 | stop the high-lift pump and mains pressure bleeds out over a few ticks; houses go dry, then a main bursts
power | 127.0.0.1:5503 | trip a feeder and that load goes dark (houses, streetlights, downtown, or the factory); grid frequency sags
widget factory | 127.0.0.1:5504 | bypass the e-stop and overspeed the line, or open the hopper gate with no car under it; the line jams
sewage | 127.0.0.1:5505 | open the storm bypass, or stop aeration and dosing; the effluent runs raw and the river plume reaches the swimming beach

Each plant's flag sits in an input-register block that only reads back while the PLC is in maintenance mode (a coil you set). The tool is pymodbus, or the bundled modbus_attack.py. Real-world parallels: Oldsmar, Florida, 2021 (the setpoint change was the attack); Maroochy Shire, Queensland, 2000 (an insider released roughly 800,000 litres of sewage via radio to pumping stations); the Ukraine grid attacks of 2015 and 2016. MITRE ATT&CK for ICS: T0855 (unauthorized command message), T0831 (manipulation of control), T0836 (modify parameter), T0813 (denial of control).

4.2 The widget factory has a second door

Alongside the process plane there is a management plane. The line-management box (factory-snmp) runs a real net-snmp agent with the shipped community strings. public reads the whole line-management subtree, and the reconciliation key is one of the OIDs. A read-write community lets you snmpset the line-enable OID and stop the line from the enterprise side. Same physical result as the Modbus path, a different plane. Default SNMP community strings on OT and network gear are a standing Shodan and pen-test finding (CWE-1392). Fix: SNMPv3 with auth and priv, no default communities, and no write access from the enterprise network.

And there is a timing puzzle: if a rail car is being loaded (the hopper gate is open) at the moment the train is routed onto the spur and derails into the factory, it is a pile-up rather than a stopped line. Throughput hard-zeros and the line jams on top of the fire.

4.3 Traffic: the bus will take an instruction from anyone

The event broker carries the signal controllers' command topic with no ACL and no auth. Publish to it and a crossroads locks all-green; the crash counter climbs a few seconds later and downtown gridlocks. A separate engineering-mode topic takes a short PIN and, on a match, publishes the flag (non-retained, so the Level 2 rotation actually takes it away). The tool is mosquitto_pub / mosquitto_sub, or traffic_attack.py. Unauthenticated MQTT brokers exposed to the internet are a standing Shodan finding; roadside signal and ITS controllers have repeatedly shipped with default or absent auth (the 2014 University of Michigan traffic-signal study). Fix: broker ACLs and auth, signed commands, and keep the control bus off any routable path.

4.4 Rail: a raw console and a shell

The loop/spur switch has a raw-TCP maintenance console with default credentials, and one of its commands hands your input straight to a shell, so it is a command-injection foothold, not a label field (CWE-78). Either one reads the maintenance key. set switch spur throws the switch; do it before the train reaches the branch, which is under the "R" of "Main Rail Line" on the map, and the train routes onto the spur, runs it down to the widget factory over about five seconds, and piles in. The factory catches fire. The Lodz tram incident of 2008 is the canonical "someone threw the switches" story. Fix: drop the raw console, or put it behind auth and a source allowlist, and never shell out on operator input.

4.5 What you should notice

Every one of these is the control channel trusting its own reachability. The PLC trusts anything on port 502. The broker trusts anything that can publish. The console trusts anything that can open the socket. The fix is almost never "patch the protocol", because you cannot. It is segmentation, a source allowlist, and moving the control plane somewhere the enterprise and the internet cannot route to.

Session 5: Recon and the Network Lanes

Goal for this session: map the town by name, then work two attacks that are a different muscle from everything else in the book, layer 2 and lateral movement.

5.1 The name server

Every target answers to a business name. A CoreDNS container is the attacker box's only resolver, authoritative for packetriver.range, with the names as CNAMEs onto the container network so dig, nslookup, curl, and nmap water.packetriver.range all follow through.

The zone answers a transfer from anyone. recon.py dns (or a plain dig axfr) dumps every host in town, plus a stray TXT record for a box that was supposed to be decommissioned, with a maintenance token in it. Open AXFR is one of the oldest external-recon wins there is, and stale records for retired kit routinely outlive the kit. MITRE T1590.002. Fix: restrict transfers to known secondaries, split an internal view from an external one, and keep secrets out of DNS.
Reverse DNS. recon.py rev pulls a PTR for every box the name server knew at boot. Cross-check it against the forward zone.
The directory. /directory and /whois?q= on the map server list every official name and its hostname. A real internal corporate directory leaks exactly this.

5.2 The Diner's open Wi-Fi

Honest scope first: Docker has no radio, and shipping something that de-authenticates real access points would be irresponsible. This lane is a switched LAN taught as open 802.11. The lesson, unencrypted traffic on a shared medium is readable and MITM-able, is the same; the RF layer is a real wireless course, not this range.

The Diner runs a cleartext rewards portal and a toy POP3 server, and a scripted patron signs in and reads mail over the segment every few seconds. A switch will not flood their unicast to you, so the attack is an active ARP-spoof man-in-the-middle: get between the patron and the access point, forward, and read the traffic. The flag is sitting in the patron's inbox. wifi_sniff.py scripts arpspoof and tcpdump. It is loud on purpose: the access point watches its own ARP cache, catches the flipped MAC, and feeds the Alert meter; a sustained spoof crosses Level 1. MITRE T1557.002 (ARP cache poisoning), T1040 (network sniffing). Fix: WPA2-Enterprise or per-client isolation, and TLS on the portal and the mail so a MITM gets ciphertext.

5.3 The SOHO router pivot: residential to OT

A house on the edge of town runs a consumer router. The homeowner is a Packet River & Southern rail engineer who works from the couch. This is the remote-worker pivot that groups like Volt Typhoon actually run, and nothing else in the range covers it.

The router has WAN-side administration reachable from the town network, the admin login is still the shipped admin / admin, and its Diagnostics page will hand you a decoded capture of the home LAN, where the resident signs in to a rail crew portal over plain HTTP on a loop. Pull the capture, read the flag, and the credential in there is reused on the real rail maintenance console. Log in with it, read the rail flag, throw the switch. soho_pcap.py scripts the router side. MITRE T1078.001 (default accounts), T1040 (the capture-page abuse), T1078 again (the credential reuse into OT). Fix: disable WAN-side administration, force a change off the default at first login, put the crew portal behind TLS, and never reuse operator credentials between a web portal and a device console.

5.4 What you should notice

Recon by name changes how you think about the range. Instead of a list of ports on 127.0.0.1 you have an organisation: a water authority, a power company, a railroad, a bank, a row of shops. That is what a real target looks like, and the zone transfer that hands it all to you in one request is a real finding you will see on real engagements.

Session 6: Now Close Every Hole

Goal for this session: run the same attacks against the same range with one flag flipped, and watch them fail. This is ./start.sh --segmented, which folds docker-compose.segmented.yml on top of the base stack. A training environment that only shows you the break is half a lesson.

6.1 What the segmented build turns off

Attack | What stops it
unauth Modbus writes | MODBUS_WRITE_OPEN=0: the PLC re-asserts its golden state every 300 ms scan, so a write is stomped within a tick
anonymous MQTT publish to the traffic topics | the broker gets a password file and an acl_file; each pkt/* topic is scoped to its rightful publisher
default PINs and console passwords | rotated off their shipped values
error-based SQLi extraction | VERBOSE_ERRORS=0
weak session tokens | WEAK_SESSIONS=0
bank alg:none | JWT_STRICT=1: the verifier rejects none and pins HS256
payment-gateway receipt IDOR | RECEIPT_AUTH=1: a bearer token is required
AS/400 blank sign-on | MOCK_AS400_HARDENED=1: a password is required
z16 default admin | MOCK_Z16_HARDENED=1: the never-revoked IBMUSER is revoked
Diner Wi-Fi sniffing | NETLAB_TLS=1: the portal and mail go TLS, so the MITM sees ciphertext
SOHO router pivot | WAN_ADMIN=0 (admin only from the home LAN), a rotated ADMIN_PASS, and PORTAL_TLS=1 so even the capture is opaque
Widget Works SNMP | SNMP_HARDENED=1: the write community is dropped and the read community moves off public

6.2 The pattern

Look down that list. There is no patch in it. Every fix is one of four things: authenticate the channel (the broker ACL, the SNMPv3 move, the bearer token), stop trusting a claim you did not verify (pin the JWT algorithm, require the AS/400 password), encrypt what was in the clear (TLS the Diner portal and the crew portal), or segment so the reachable thing is not the sensitive thing (the Modbus re-assert, WAN-admin off, the OT network drop at Alert Level 4).

That is the whole defensive syllabus for this class of target. The boring attacks have boring fixes. The hard part in the real world is never knowing the fix; it is inventory, ownership, and the political will to change a default on a system somebody is afraid to touch.

6.3 What is still open, and why

The segmented build's detection story is the gateway log tailer, the broker ACLs, and the PLC golden re-assert. A dedicated inline IDS (Suricata watching a span port) is on the roadmap and not shipped, because a container on a Docker bridge only sees its own traffic and broadcast; a real sensor needs a mirror interface or a router container, which is a topology change. The book calls that out rather than shipping theatre.

6.4 Exercise

Pick three techniques you landed in Sessions 2 through 5. For each, before you run it against the segmented build, write down which of the four fix patterns you expect stopped it and how you would confirm the control is actually on (not just configured). Then run it and check yourself against docs/verification.md Section D.

Session 7: Capstone and Incident Response

Two halves. First, chain the whole town for a high score, quietly. Then sit on the other side of the table and work the incident.

7.1 The capstone run

One run, timed from your first arm. The scoring rewards chaining distinct techniques on one subsystem, so plan the order. A worked example of the shape, not a script:

Recon by name. Pull the zone transfer and the reverse zone. Read the directory. Now you have the org chart, and you have spent almost no heat doing it.
Get a residential foothold. The SOHO router on its default login, its capture page, the reused rail credential. You are into OT without touching a single loud web target.
Stage the rail derail but do not fire it. Read the console key. Wait for the loading cycle.
Work Main Street for the chain bonus while the town is calm. The quiet techniques first (IDOR, the exposed backup, the .git leak), then the mediums.
Time the loud moves to the events. Not while the news crew is filming your subsystem. Not with an inspector on site. The parade is the one exception: if you are going to hijack a signal, the parade is when it counts.
The bank last, or whenever you have accepted that Alert Level 2 is coming and you have already used every default credential you were going to need.

Compare your run to a loud one: run the same techniques again without regard for the events or the meter, and watch the speed multiplier collapse and the stealth bonus disappear. The delta is the lesson.

7.2 The tabletop

Now you are the SOC. Reset the town, have someone else run a chain against it, and work the response from the artefacts you actually have:

Question | Where the answer lives
When did it start, and from where? | the gateway JSON access log (gw-logs volume): tool user-agents, 4xx bursts, path spray
What did the Alert meter see, and when? | alert.blue_actions in the state snapshot; pkt/alert/level on the bus
Which subsystems are off-golden right now? | the map, and GET /api/state
Was OT reached directly or through a pivot? | status.sh containment probe; which web target went loud first
Did the blue team's automatic responses help or just annoy the attacker? | compare a run where Level 2 fired mid-chain against one where it did not

Then the recovery: ./reset.sh per subsystem, verify golden against docs/verification.md Section C, and write the two-paragraph "what we would change" that every real incident ends with. For Packet River the answer is almost always in Session 6's four patterns. Saying which one, and naming the specific default or missing control, is the exercise.

7.3 Where to go next

Widgetorium goes deeper on the web half; Cross Creek goes deeper on the ICS half with real EtherNet/IP and S7comm and a proper Purdue-model network. If you want the RF layer under Session 5's Wi-Fi lane, that is a wireless course, not this range. And if you want the mainframe half for real, that is a career, and it is the one the author has.

About the Author

Britley Hoff is the Technology Owner for Linux on IBM Z at Blue Cross Blue Shield of South Carolina: ten years of hands-on mainframe work, RACF, z/OS, TN3270, TSO, z/VM, on top of twenty-five years in Linux and general IT, including Linux on Z. GED, no college, certifications and real-world experience instead. Also an author, a maker, and a self-described Sovereign AI advocate.

Packet River is the third range in a set. Widgetorium is a deliberately vulnerable web-application lab with its own "Widgetorium 101" syllabus. Cross Creek is an ICS/OT range, a mock reverse-osmosis water plant and a power substation on real Modbus, EtherNet/IP, and S7comm, with a "Cross Creek 101" syllabus. The three share a toolchain, a safety posture, and a house style: every weakness is real, every weakness has a working hardened counter-build, and every command in the instructor edition was run against the actual containers before it went to print.

The bias in all three is the same, and it is worth stating plainly. The interesting attacks are not the clever ones. They are default credentials, a protocol with no authentication, a flat network, a system nobody wanted to touch. That is what is working right now, on water systems and substations and banks and the boxes that still run payroll. A range that teaches the boring stuff well is more useful than one that hopes a zero-day falls in your lap.

Links

Source and issues: https://github.com/wren-creator/packetriver
Community and discussion: britleydev.slack.com
Consulting, training, and talks: https://britleyhoffconsulting.com, britleyhoff@britleyhoffconsulting.com

Packet River is licensed GNU GPL-3.0. If it is useful to you or your team, there is a tip jar in the corner of the map. No pressure, and it never gates anything in the game.